Guide to the Victor G. Bloede Papers, 1952-1983 and undated RL.00120
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Victor G. Bloede papers
1952-1983 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bloede, Victor G.
RL.00120
1 Linear Feet
Victor Bloede (1920-1999) was an advertising executive who served as President and Chief Executive Officer (1968-1974), and Chairman (1971-1983), of the Benton & Bowles agency. He retired in 1983. The Victor Bloede Papers span the years 1952-1983, with the bulk spanning 1962-1983, and consist primarily of speeches given during Bloede's tenure as President, then Chairman, of Benton & Bowles (B&B), as well as speeches delivered during 1973 when Bloede served as Chairman of the American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA or 4-A's). Also included are a portion of the autobiography of Atherton Hobler, one of the co-founders of B&B, and correspondence relating to the anticommunist newsletter Counterattack. Topics included in the speeches include corporate finances and budget performance, television commericials, advertising effectiveness, management and business ethics. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
700 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Victor G. Bloede Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2004.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1920 Jan. 31 Born Victor Gustav Bloede, Baltimore, Md.
1941 Graduated, University of Maryland
1943-1945 Army Air Force, promoted to rank of Captain
1950 Copywriter, Benton & Bowles
1955 Vice President, Benton & Bowles
1968-1974 President and Chief Executive Officer, Benton & Bowles
1971-1983 Chairman, Benton & Bowles
1973 Chairman, American Association of Advertising Agencies
1983 Retired from Benton & Bowles The Full Service Advertising Agency published
1999 Feb. 10 Died, Boca Raton, Fla.
Victor Bloede is said to be the first executive from the creative side of the advertising business to become the Chief Executive Officer of a major advertising agency. He is credited with building Maxwell House coffee, Crest toothpaste, Zest soap, Pampers diapers, and Charmin tissue into major brands. Bloede also served on the Board and the Advisory Committee of the Professional Golfers Association (PGA).
Collection Overview
The Victor Bloede Papers span the years 1952-1983, with the bulk spanning 1962-1983, and consist primarily of speeches given during Bloede's tenure as President, then Chairman, of Benton & Bowles (B&B), as well as speeches delivered during 1973 when Bloede served as Chairman of the American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA or 4-A's). Also included are a portion of the autobiography of Atherton Hobler, one of the co-founders of B&B, and correspondence relating to the anticommunist newsletter Counterattack. Topics included in the speeches include corporate finances and budget performance, television commericials, advertising effectiveness, management and business ethics.
Related Material
Related material may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives
Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- Management; Benton & Bowles; American Association of Advertising Agencies; Bloede, Victor G.; Bloede, Victor G. (Victor Gustave), 1920-1999; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Hobler, Atherton
- General Files, 1952 and undated
  - Atherton Hobler autobiography, Ch. 1-4, undated (Box 1)
  - Counterattack newsletter and correspondence, 1952 (Box 1)
- Speeches, 1962-1983
  - General
    - 1962-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1962 Aug. 29, Effective Advertising. Air Express presentation (Box 1)
    - 1962 June 8, Speech to Waldorf graduates (Box 1)
    - 1962, Savings Bank talk (Box 1)
    - 1963 July 18, Ad Age workshop (Box 1)
    - 1964 Nov. 11, Experiences in Evaluating the Cumulative Effects of Advertising Campaigns. Speech to American Association of Advertising Agencies meeting (Box 1)
    - 1964 Feb. 28, Speech to Southwest Council of 4-A's (Box 1)
    - 1967 Mar. 23, Association of National Advertisers (ANA) TV Workshop (Box 1)
    - 1967 Nov. 16, Today's Message for Tomorrow's TV Commercials. Television Bureau of Advertising talk (Box 1)
    - 1968 Aug. 2, The One Thing I Would Most Like Creative People to Know. Ad Age Creative Workshop (Box 1)
    - 1968 Sept. 5, Where Do We Go from Here? Pet Food Institute (Box 1)
    - 1967 Sept. 12, Association of National Advertisers (ANA) (Box 1)
    - 1968 Oct. 17, If I Were the Client...Getting Agency Help in Implementing Marketing Programs. National Industrial Conference Board (Box 1)
    - 1969 Jan. 8, S.C. Johnson talk (Box 1)
    - 1969 May 7, The Creative Scene--1969 and Beyond. Association of Canadian Advertisers (Box 1)
    - 1969 May 27, The Advertising Agency of the Future. International Conference of Sales Promotion Executives (Box 1)
    - 1969 Dec. 7-10, How the Agencies Look at Agency Evaluation Procedures. Association of National Advertisers (Box 1)
    - 1970-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1970 Apr. 15, Is There An Ad Agency in My Future? Association of National Advertisers Seminar on Television Advertising Management (Box 1)
    - 1970 May 12, The Look of Advertising in the 70s. S.C. Johnson & Son International Meeting (Box 1)
    - 1970 June 30, Dentsu talk (Box 1)
    - 1970 Sept. 23, Advertising Business Trends. ANA Advanced Advertising Management Seminar (Box 1)
    - 1970 Oct. 21, 4-A's Eastern Annual Conference (Box 1)
    - 1971 Mar. 18, Interchange of Information Regarding Availability of Partial Agency Services Among 70 Larger AAAA Agencies. ANA Workshop (Box 1)
    - 1971 June 7, Johnson Wax International Product Management Conference (Box 1)
    - 1971 Oct. 26, Texaco Circle talk (Box 1)
    - 1972 Mar. 18, The Copy Crisis: A New Look at an Old Problem. AAAA Annual Meeting (Box 1)
    - 1972 May 25, Texaco Round Table (Box 1)
    - 1972 Sept. 12, Talk to London clients (Box 1)
    - 1974 May 17, AAAA Annual Meeting (Box 1)
    - 1975 Apr. 29, Color Marketing Group (Box 1)
    - 1976 June 7, International Advertising in the Mid-Seventies. American Marketing Associaton Conference (Box 1)
    - 1983 Nov. 22, The Advertising Man and His Social Responsibility (Box 1)
  - Benton & Bowles Shareholder Meetings
    - 1967 Apr. 10, Untitled (Box 1)
    - 1967 Aug. 21, Account Management and the Creative Process (Box 1)
    - 1968 Oct. 25, Management Leadership (Box 1)
    - 1969-1983, Untitled speeches (Box 1)
  - Benton & Bowles Annual International Conference
    - 1969-1982, Untitled speeches, 1 of 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1969-1982, Untitled speeches (continued), 2 of 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Speeches made as Chairman of AAAA
    - 1973 Apr. 24, The Freedom to Advertise. American Newspaper Publishers Association (Box 2)
    - 1973 May 30, Institute of Advertising Studies (Box 2)
    - 1973 June 11, The Maturing of Madison Avenue. Association of National Advertisers (Box 2)
    - 1973 Sept. 19, AAAA Financial Management Group (Box 2)
    - 1973 Sept. 20, Pharmaceutical Advertising Club (Box 2)
    - 1973 Oct. 2, Premium Advertising Association (Box 2)
    - 1973 Oct. 15, AAAA Western Region Annual Meeting (Box 2)
    - 1973 Oct. 31, AAAA Central Region Annual Meeting (Box 2)